[Music]
so a couple of weeks ago David fuller of
rebel wisdom he is the documentary
filmmaker and journalist who did the
first kind of full-length documentary
about Jordan Peterson and he also did
another documentary called a glitch in
the matrix he approached me and asked me
if I would have a conversation with him
and maybe write something for rebel
wisdom and at that point I decided okay
I am fed up with talking about Jordan
Peterson I've done it for a whole year
I've been thinking of talking about
Jordan Peterson and I'm tired of the
whole game I need to move on and I need
to just you know quietly reflect on his
works on my own you know you get a lot
of feedback on the ideas you put out
there and people are anything from
extraordinarily complimentary to
extremely insulting and that's just the
way it is but I decided I had enough of
it now I wanted to move on then David
fuller gave me a call and we had this
long conversation and I wrote this essay
called Jordan Peterson and the black
tide of mysticism and I thought after
writing that essay I got it right this
time
I've said what I wanted to say they're
all my other previous essays some of
them were not bad but but this one was
like I hit the nail on the head so it's
very happy about that and Peterson
himself tweeted the article and David
fuller you know put it on his site and
put our conversation an edited version
of our conversation on the site and so
so I've been getting a lot of you know
feedback and I'm still in the game so to
speak so I wanted to have a make a sort
of meta commentary on our discussion my
discussion with David fuller and about
my article because what you find is one
discussion leads to another discussion
and yet you have this sort
endlessly expanding web of ideas and
actually after the discussion with Fleur
I felt a little bit frustrated a bit
like there were there were so many
loosened things I wanted to say I was
happier with the essay but I still got
more things to say
so the basic subject of our discussion
was why does Peterson cause such
polarized extreme reactions among people
why can't you be for example just a
critic of Peterson and like something he
says and not like something else it
seems to be this extreme reactions to
his work and to his person and I I think
it's interesting mmm to think about why
that is so I consider Peterson to be in
the lineage of Carl Jung and this makes
him problematic to a lot of people let's
say why is this well Jung is a scientist
who explored mysticism and in our world
of categories of people you know a lot
of people public scientists have a very
negative perspective of Mississippi and
similarly a lot of people who are
invested in or interested in mysticism
and my business ISM I mean a few things
but what is mysterious what we don't
understand and mysticism in terms of
being the perhaps hidden aspect or
esoteric aspect of religion because
religion has an exit
and an esoteric aspect and the Mystics
usually speak in terms that we don't
understand maybe esoteric terms even
though I would argue that mystics are
far more empirical than to the pure
rationalist you know think or believe
and this is a misunderstanding there
seems to be two worldviews there seems
to be a scientific worldview and there
seems to be a religious / mystical
worldview and those seem to be two
realms which are not allowed to overlap
perhaps for good reason but there's a
problem with the scientific worldview
when it makes judgments about religion
the problem is that it's a worldview and
a worldview and it is something that is
enclosed in a set of you know principles
and axioms and fixed ideas whereas the
scientific investigation by nature
should be an open investigation there
should be no taboos about knowledge and
yet there are so my article I talked
about the relationship between Jung and
Freud and Freud who who rejected Jung
because of his interest in the occult in
mysticism and Jung who regarded for it
is a kind of a tragic character because
he couldn't come come to grips with this
aspect of reality that he reduced
everything to beautiful complex drives
he was afraid of what he called the
black tides of mysticism so when I was a
student at university there were a lot
of teachers
or a few teacher I listen to and they
have much appreciation for Freud and
they're tended to look down and young
because Young was a mystic and a
scientist so again
Peterson would not doesn't usually refer
to himself as a mystic and probably
wouldn't refer to himself as a mistake
because he's in this let's say boxing
ring with all kinds of hardcore hard
science hard rationality types and he
wants to explain mythology the Bible in
a way that they can understand and he's
been incredibly successful he has a huge
following of atheists so you have all
these atheists either coming back to
religion finding traditional religion or
just becoming curious about mythological
stories and ancient mythological stories
and instead of doing what the new the
atheist did which was just to dismiss
these stories as being irrational fairy
tales Peter says no no no no no these
stories are deep these stories are
profound these stories matter to
everybody these stories are the
underlying metaphysics of our culture
and science is nested within that
science is not the overcoming of
religion or mysticism
science is actually a creation of the
intense search for truth which has been
articulated in religion and religions in
stories religious stories religious
edicts religious injunctions about how
to live so the funny thing is that Peter
Cygnus is talking to all these hardcore
rationalists and he can speak their
language
what he's also appealing to a lot of
religious people people who are
religious traditionalists you know like
the Catholics he's had various
discussions with with with Catholics and
the Catholics are saying you know you're
a Catholic I forget this guy he was
talking to Patrick often and in their
discussion
Patrick often says you're a you're a
Catholic
you're a future Catholic and then he
starts to suggest that Nietzsche and
young all of these thinkers are
heretical in some sense why doesn't he
just become a Catholic Peterson replies
and I think this was a beautiful moment
said maybe it's true maybe carlion and
nature or heretics but what makes you
think you aren't one so coughin didn't
like that very much
he was immediately silenced because in
many ways were all heretics role we all
we all go against our own better
principles unless were saintly people
unless we're the Buddha Christ
unless we're completely realized we're
all heretics we're all you know sinners
these kind of expressions like to say
you're a sinner is it sounds very quaint
to postmodernists it sounds very almost
ridiculous but again that's because they
don't understand the etymology of these
things or that are the depth of them or
the meaning of them the word sin means
to miss the mark you know and we all
missed the mark or an overall not always
on top of the game so that means we're
all sinners we're all heretics and so
you can't come here and tell me that
just by joining this organization called
that the Catholic Church though suddenly
you'll become beyond reproach
anyway so in my article I talked about
that I've talked about his his
attraction to traditionalists and yet
the frustration they have with him as
well because he's not making absolutist
claims about religion I mean about
membership to religion and he doesn't go
to church even though he's sympathetic
to church people and to churches and to
religious traditions I also suggested
that this makes him a bit more
postmodern so anyway Peterson is
problematic to practically everybody
which is interesting right he's
problematic to traditionalists because
he doesn't go to church
he's problematic too
modernists because he's interested in
religion
he's problematic to postmodernists
because he values tradition and he's
problematic to the extreme left and the
extreme right because he's a vicious
critic of both of them especially the
extreme left so here you have a person
whose point of view is not fixed rigid
unthinking and yet at the same time it's
quite it's quite a coherent picture that
he paints it's quite a it's it's it's
more than well thought out it's
something that he's thought about for
years and years and years and he has
managed to articulate in a way that is
both easy to understand but not
simplistic let's take the notion of
cleaning your room this is the most
basic injunction and at the same time
it's a metaphor and a metaphor is
complex you know your room is not just
four walls in a bed in a desk
your room is something far more
mysterious mystical your room is the
place where you dream your room is your
shelter your mind is like a room so the
room is a microcosm for your mind so on
one level it's it's an injunction - it's
a very simplistic injunction - no to be
a to be a decent clean person right and
then next level is psychological to be
an ort well-ordered person in your mind
and then the next level is spiritual
let's say a clean room if you have a
clean room in your spiritual University
you you can you're like a mirror you
know you can see clearly so anyway you
could you can you can look at his his
thought from whichever perspective that
works for you there was one guy I think
it's called sorting yourself out it he
was trying to stop you know watching
porn and smoking marijuana so that's how
he approached Peterson how'd it get my
life together there's other people who
approached Peterson you know from a more
abstract point of view and you know are
interested in is his theory his
theoretical ideas about you know about
about about the Bible and about
psychology or they're just you know more
intellectually set on fire by Peterson
but Peterson's not never a mere
intellectual which is great because he's
concrete he never he will never rely on
mere theory he's a scientific thinker in
the sense that the theory has to be
tested out in reality in real life which
is the opposite of it let's say uh a
postmodern thinker like Z Zack who says
something like what we need today is
more theory and less action Peterson
saying logos you know speech has to be
aligned with action with reality so I
think that that that the
this kind of extremely abstract
postmodern intellectuals they've they
just he just rubs in the wrong way and
one of the reasons is as I've suggested
is that he's found a way to unite the
high abstraction of philosophy with the
kitchen sink with your room with the
most earthly qualities in Taoism they
call that joining heaven and earth or as
I think a lot of the theorists are
trapped in this sort of abstract world
up here and can't bring it down here I
think and I think something to do with
Peterson's success has has to do with
his ability to do that and it's
surprising it's very surprising because
he's unlikely he's the most unlikely
superstar you could possibly imagine
he's down-to-earth and unpretentious and
he is articulated Jung's idea of the
shadow in a way that people can
understand and it's very appropriate
today it's extremely appropriate our
articulation is to have a look at yoga
shadow especially in the age of Trump
Trump to me represents the the shadow of
Western civilization he's the
unconscious man whose primary interest
is power
so when Trump was elected there is this
void and the conscious man needs to step
in so I'm not saying that Peterson is
the conscious man I'm saying that the
conscious man has to step in
I think that's what I'll say for today
thank you very much for listening